Finding Aid for Development Council (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Development Council (University of Michigan) records
1951-1985
University of Michigan. Development Council.
87154 Bimu C532 2
Organizational records; minutes of the board of directors, and of the steering committee; and subject files detailing fund raising activities and campus fraternities (resulting from association of staff member with Sigma Phi).
3.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Development Council first transferred records in 1959 (Donor No. 3576 ). The bulk of the records, however, were received from the office of the Vice-President for Development and Communications (Donor No. 3813 ) in 1986.
The records are open for research use.
The Development Council was an organization of university alumni established in 1953 to secure private financial support to supplement the university's traditional funding sources. When it was founded, the council consisted of a large body of volunteer solicitors guided by a volunteer board of directors. The group's day to day activities were supported by a small development office whose staff was paid for out of funds raised by the council. The council's first major project was the Michigan Annual Fund, a yearly solicitation of University of Michigan alumni. The Michigan Annual Fund (MAF) was quickly supplemented by special projects to cultivate foundation and corporate support.
In the early 1960s the university decided to launch a major fund raising project, the $55 Million Campaign. The project was the responsibility of the vice-president for university relations and in order to accomplish it, his office largely absorbed the development office. The council itself became relatively dormant during this period. At the conclusion of the $55 Million Campaign university officials realized the ongoing importance of the council, and helped revive and revitalize the volunteer element of the organization.
When Jon Cosovich was made Vice President for Development and University Relations in 1983, the university began to rely increasingly on a centralized staff in the area of development. Although not officially dissolved, the Development Council stopped meeting in 1985.
The Development Council records date from 1951 to 1985 and measure 3.5 linear feet. They are arranged in a two series: Board of Directors and an Alphabetical File. The records are most notable for organizational documents from the early 1950s and mid- to late-1960s, long runs of minutes from the board of directors (1953-1985) and steering committee (1968-1980), and correspondence from the development office (1951-1963). Surprisingly, there is a small but interesting body of records regarding fraternities and sororities, particularly Sigma Phi. This is located in the correspondence and results from the association of one of the Development Office staff with Sigma Phi.
Subjects:
Sigma Phi. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.StudentsSocieties, etc.; University of Michigan. Development Council.; University of Michigan--Finance.Finance.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Development and Communication.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Educational fund raising--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Board of Directors
  - Meetings
    - Regular
      - 1953-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1968-1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1971
        - February 5-6 (Box 1)
        - May 21-22 (Box 1)
        - November 5-6 (Box 1)
      - 1972
        - January 21 (Box 1)
        - June 1 (Box 1)
      - 1973
        - January 25 (Box 1)
        - June 21 (Box 1)
        - October 11 (Box 1)
      - 1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975
        - January 23 (Box 1)
        - June 2 (Box 1)
        - October 30 (Box 1)
      - 1976
        - January 29 (Box 1)
        - June 2 (Box 1)
        - October 21 (Box 1)
      - 1977
        - January 26 (Box 1)
        - June 9 (Box 1)
        - November 11 (Box 1)
      - 1978
        - January 27 (Box 1)
        - February 3 (Box 1)
        - May 25 (Box 1)
        - October 13 (Box 1)
      - 1979
        - January 25 (Box 1)
        - May 24 (Box 1)
        - October 11 (Box 1)
      - 1980
        - April 3 (Box 1)
        - June 12 (Box 1)
        - October 9 (Box 1)
      - 1981
        - March 26 (Box 2)
        - June 11 (Box 2)
        - December 11 (Box 2)
      - 1982
        - January 3 (Box 2)
        - October 28 (Box 2)
      - 1983
        - March 24 (Box 2)
        - April 28-29 (Box 2)
        - June 9 (Box 2)
      - 1985
        - January 25 (Box 2)
    - Joint meetings with Alumni Fund, 1958-1964 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists
    - 1953-1961 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1983 (Box 2)
- Alpha File
  - General
    - [background and organizational structure of Development Council], circa 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      [includes $55 Million Campaign reference material]
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - All Alumni Solicitation Planning Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports
    - 1952/53-1957, 1967/68-1969/70; 1971/72; 1980/81-1982/83 (Box 1)
  - Chairmen (list of), 1953-1979 (Box 2)
  - Charters and organization, 1951-1979; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Committee members
    - 1963-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 2)
  - Corporate Relations Committee, 1978-1981 (Box 2)
  - Corporation program (proposed), 1954 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1963; 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Deferred Giving
    - Committee, 1969-1970; 1972; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Review Committee, 1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Steering Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Development Newsletter, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Developments,1954-1957, 1960-1966 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee
    - 1953-1957 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 3)
    - (December 2), 1981 (Box 3)
    - (June 10), 1982 (Box 3)
  - Foundation Relations Committee, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising policy, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Interim Committee meeting, November 1, 1968 (Box 3)
  - News About the University, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Operations Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Planning Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Reorganization, 1968-1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - "Report of Study of Development and Financial Programs Conducted by Eleven Leading Universities" (prepared by Alan W. MacCarthy), November 26, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Review Committee (charge), 1969 (Box 3)
  - Review Committee on Corporations and Foundations (background material and report), 1969 (Box 3)
  - Review Committee on Deferred Giving (report), May 1969 (Box 3)
  - Review Committee on the Michigan Alumni Fund (report), April 30, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Review Committee on the Presidents Club (report), May 5, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Steering Committee meetings
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - 1971, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - 1972, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - 1973, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - 1974, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - 1975, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - 1976, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1977, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - 1978, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - 1979, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Photograph [organizing meeting, October 1953] (Box 4)